<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml packageId="knb-lter-nwt.124.3"
  system="https://pasta.edirepository.org"
  xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1"
  xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.1/eml.xsd">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication"
    order="allowFirst" scope="document" system="https://pasta.edirepository.org">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=nwt,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
      <permission>write</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier system="https://doi.org">doi:10.6073/pasta/989918ab79a58e7852a630e11da4852f</alternateIdentifier>
    <title>Soil temperature data for Saddle, 1992 - 1993.</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Steven K</givenName>
        <surName>Schmidt</surName>
      </individualName>
      <electronicMailAddress>steven.schmidt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Steven K</givenName>
        <surName>Schmidt</surName>
      </individualName>
      <electronicMailAddress>steven.schmidt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <role>principalInvestigator</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>1993</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>Trace gas samples were collected from 3 alpine tundra vegetation community types (dry meadow, moist meadow, wet meadow) on Niwot Ridge during the summer months of 1992 and 1993. In addition, samples were collected from a set of control and nitrogen amended plots in both dry and wet meadow community types. Soil temperatures were measured in conjunction with the trace gas sampling.</abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>soil microenvironment</keyword>
      <keyword>Meteorology and Climatology</keyword>
      <keyword>trace gas sampling</keyword>
      <keyword>alpine tundra</keyword>
      <keyword>dry meadow</keyword>
      <keyword>moist meadow</keyword>
      <keyword>wet meadow</keyword>
      <keyword>saddle</keyword>
      <keyword>Niwot Ridge LTER</keyword>
      <keyword>NWT</keyword>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>soil temperature</keyword>
      <keyword>microclimate</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER controlled vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>
  This information is released under the Creative Commons license -
  Attribution - CC BY (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).
  The consumer of these data (“Data User” herein) is required to cite it
  appropriately in any publication that results from its use. The Data
  User should realize that these data may be actively used by others for
  ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary to prevent
  duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the authors
  of these data if any questions about methodology or results occur.
  Where appropriate, the Data User is encouraged to consider
  collaboration or co-authorship with the authors. The Data User should
  realize that misinterpretation of data may occur if used out of
  context of the original study. While substantial efforts are made to
  ensure the accuracy of data and associated documentation, complete
  accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made
  available "as is." The Data User should be aware, however,
  that data are updated periodically and it is the responsibility of the
  Data User to check for new versions of the data. The data authors and
  the repository where these data were obtained shall not be liable for
  damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of the data. Thank
  you.
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>The study sites were located in the Niwot Ridge Saddle. Original data are stored in Ramaley Hall.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-105.5923174</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-105.5891563</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>40.05481558</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>40.04903177</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1992-06-08</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>1993-08-18</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <maintenance>
      <description>The original iteration of the documentation and header sections of this file was developed by Rick Ingersoll and Mike Sannes in late December 1993. The 1992 and 1993 data were added to the data section of the file at this time and the file was put under sccs control on 20 December 1993.[RCI 20 December 1993] Editorial revisions provided by SKS on 10 January 1994 were incorporated into the documentation section on that date.[RCI 10 January 1994] Trace gas plot locations surveyed by Tim Bardsley and Mike Hartman on 6 July 1994 were added to the comments section on 14 July 1994. [RCI 14 July 1994] A description of the methods used was provided by Steve Schmidt on 15 July 1994 and this information and the associated citation were incorporated into the documentation section on 20 July 1994.[RCI 20 July 1994] Fertilization plot locations surveyed by Tim Bardsley and Mike Hartman on 13 July and 7 September 1994 were added to the comments section on 14 September 1994.[RCI 14 September 1994] The title, keywords, and units were edited, labels shortened, and definitions added.[HCH 13 May 2016] Temperature units changed to celsius.[HCH 27 April 2017]Niwot metadata converted via script to EML[ATW 2019-10-28]</description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
      <positionName>Information Manager</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>4001 Discovery Drive, UCB 450</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>University of Colorado</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Boulder</city>
        <administrativeArea>CO</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>80303</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>lternwt@colorado.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>https://nwt.lternet.edu/</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>The 1992 data were supplied in the form of an ASCII file by Melany Fisk in early December 1993; these were not entered using an EasyEntry program. The 1993 were entered using an EasyEntry form. Consequently, it was necessary to modify the format of the processed data for the 2 years in order to make them compatible so that both could be incorporated into the data section for the present file. Fluxes of methane and nitrous oxide are collected during non- snow covered periods from static chambers (Matson et al. 1992). These chambers consist of 25-cm diameter PVC rings (bases) that are 20 cm tall with a detachable ABS (acrylonitrile-butadiene-styrene) plastic cover. The ABS cover was fitted with a single injection port and another small port to equalize pressure during sampling. Once the chambers were sealed, duplicate gas samples were removed through a septum with 10-cm^3 gas-tight glass syringes equipped with 3-way stopcocks. Gas samples were collected every 45 minutes over a 3-hour period. Samples were analyzed on gas chromatographs.</para>
          <para>Plot/base number codes ending with the character 'A' are for air samples; they were not associated with specific base numbers. The initial character in the plot/base number code is either 'T' (transect) or 'B' (Bowman plots). The second character in the plot/base number code is either '1', '2', or '3' (transect number) if the initial character is a 'T'; or 'D' or 'W' (community type, i.e., dry or wet meadow) if the initial character is 'B'. The third character in the plot/base number code is either 'D', 'M', or 'W' (community type with M indicating moist meadow) if the initial character is a 'T'; or 'C' (control) or 'N' (nitrogen amended) if the initial character is a 'B'. The fourth character in the plot/base number code is the base number. The character 'X' is used for the base number for the 1992 data, since temperatures for that year were only associated with a particular plot, not a base number.</para>
          <para>Tim Bardsley and Mike Hartman conducted a rudimentary survey of some of the more heavily used NWT LTER research plots in 1994 in order to reference the plots to established objects/points on Niwot Ridge. A Silva Ranger compass was used with E declination set at 12 degrees; the accuracy of the bearings is +/- 3 degrees. All distances were measured across the ground surface (not at a fixed horizontal level); such distances are accurate to +/- 2%. Each trace gas plot consisted of an area (with an undefined outer boundary) of comparatively heterogeneous composition (with respect to plant species composition, or plant community type). Bearings and distances were from fixed points of reference to the approximate center of the plots (i.e., the center of the bases within the plot). In some cases (T1D, T2D, T1M, T1W), bearings were taken from the approximate center of the plot to a fixed reference point, usually because the plots were not visible from the fixed reference point. In such cases, the reverse bearing was calculated and, for the sake of consistency, is listed below. The original Bardsley/Hartman field notes contain crude diagrams indicating the relative orientation of and distances between the bases within a plot; bases were generally within 4 m of the center of the plot. This information is not reported here but these notes are on file with the NWT LTER data manager. The plot code, bearing (degrees) from indicated reference point to center of plot, distance (meters) from indicated reference point to center of the plot, and number of bases in plot follow:</para>
          <para>T1D,192 (wind turbine centerline),146.1 (wind turbine SW corner),4</para>
          <para>T2D,30 (Saddle grid stake 60A),28.60 (Saddle grid stake 60A),4</para>
          <para>T3D,40 (Saddle grid stake 78),50.5 (Saddle grid stake 78),5</para>
          <para>T1M,254 (wind turbine centerline),48.8 (wind turbine SW corner),4</para>
          <para>T2M,87 (Saddle grid stake 59),24.25 (Saddle grid stake 59),4</para>
          <para>T3M,41 (Saddle grid stake 77),33.44 (Saddle grid stake 77),8</para>
          <para>T1W,220 (wind turbine centerline),153.20 (wind turbine SW corner),4</para>
          <para>T2W,230 (Saddle grid stake 67),17.3 (Saddle grid stake 67),4</para>
          <para>T3W,25 (Saddle grid stake 77),23.20 (Saddle grid stake 77),4</para>
          <para>The fertilized wet meadow plots were surveyed on 13 July 1994 using the same methodology. The bearing from the northwest corner of the c1 wet meadow plot to the centerline of the wind turbine was 202 degrees. Thus, the bearing from the centerline of the wind turbine to the northwest corner of the c1 wet meadow plot was 22 degrees. The distance form the northwest corner of the c1 wet meadow plot to the southwest corner of the base of the wind turbine was 278.2 meters. A crude map of the relationships among the dry meadow plots was provided by Bill Bowman and that map is on file with the LTER data manager. Plot n1 was oriented west and south of c1. Plot np1 was approximately due south of c1. The following plots were approximately due west of np1 (with the most proximal listed first): np2, p1, c2, p2, c3, p3, c4, np4, and c5. The bearing from the northwest corner of c1 to the northwest corner of c5 was 309 degrees. South of this row, and oriented approximately from west to east were plots n2, n3, np5, np4, n4, np3, n5, and p5. The plots n2, n5, and p5 were slightly out of line with the other plots in the row; the bearings from the northwest corner of c1 to the northwest corner of these plots were 292, 249, and 239 degrees, respectively. Note that a band of willows (approximately L-shaped) separates plots n5 and p5 from c2, p1, and np2. The distances (meters) reported below are between the northwest corner of c1 and the northwest corner of the given plot:</para>
          <para>n1,3.55</para>
          <para>np1,3.27</para>
          <para>np2,6.19</para>
          <para>p1,8.51</para>
          <para>c2,12.65</para>
          <para>p2,15.59</para>
          <para>c3,18.84</para>
          <para>p3,22.75</para>
          <para>c4,24.89</para>
          <para>p4,27.09</para>
          <para>c5,29.55</para>
          <para>n2,32.39</para>
          <para>n3,28.45</para>
          <para>np5,26.20</para>
          <para>np4,23.63</para>
          <para>n4,19.95</para>
          <para>np3,15.55</para>
          <para>n5,15.00</para>
          <para>p5,16.75</para>
          <para>Tim Bardsley and Mike Hartman conducted a rudimentary survey of the fertilized dry meadow plots on 7 September 1994. A less sophisticated compass was used for this survey and, consequently, all bearings reported below are for magnetic, not true, north; a declination of 11.5 degrees should be added to the former to convert to the latter. The bearing from the northeast corner of the c1 dry meadow plot to the centerline of the wind turbine was 345 degrees. Thus, the bearing from the centerline of the wind turbine to the northeast corner of the c1 dry meadow plot was 165 degrees. The distance from the northeast corner of the c1 dry meadow plot to the southwest corner of the base of the wind turbine was 231.0 meters. The bearings (degrees) and distances (meters) reported below are from the northeast corner of the c1 dry meadow plot to the northeast corner of the given plot:</para>
          <para>np1,259,3.37</para>
          <para>p1,178,3.12</para>
          <para>n1,209,6.90</para>
          <para>np2,192,10.46</para>
          <para>p2,212,10.83</para>
          <para>c2,222,12.20</para>
          <para>n2,239,13.58</para>
          <para>n3,232,17.41</para>
          <para>np3,246,19.26</para>
          <para>c3,199,31.47</para>
          <para>p3,211,31.62</para>
          <para>c4,214,32.50</para>
          <para>np4,221,33.41</para>
          <para>p4,228,34.60</para>
          <para>c5,232,36.48</para>
          <para>n4,234,39.07</para>
          <para>p5,206,35.55</para>
          <para>n5,207,37.74</para>
          <para>np5,205,39.20</para>
          <para>Note that the plot code nomenclature used in the surveys is slightly different than the plot code nomenclature used elsewhere in this file. The code BDN2, for example, would be equivalent to n2 in the second of the 2 listings for the fertilized plot locations above. See /data1/Datman/Nwtdata/tracegas.ss for associated nitrous oxide and methane concentration data.</para>
          <para>Additional soil temperature data for Niwot Ridge can be found in the files soiltemp.ts and snftemps.dw in /data1/Datman/Nwtdata on niwotlter. This research was supported by the Environmental Protection Agency (R819448-01-1).</para>
          <para/>
          <para>CITATIONS:</para>
          <para>[1]Matson, P.A., S.T. Gower, C. Volkmann, C. Billow, and C.C. Grier. 1992. Soil nitrogen cycling and nitrous oxide flux in a Rocky Mountain Douglas-fir forest: effects of fertilization, irrigation, and carbon addition. Biogeochemistry 18:101-117.</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>LTER: The Niwot Ridge LTER Research Program 1998-2004: Controls on the Structure, Function &amp; Interactions of Alpine &amp; Subalpine Ecosystems of the Colorado Front Range</title>
      <personnel>
        <organizationName>Niwot Ridge LTER</organizationName>
        <role>pointOfContact</role>
      </personnel>
      <funding>National Science Foundation:9810218</funding>
    </project>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>soiltemp.ss.data.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Soil temperature data for Saddle, 1992 - 1993.</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>soiltemp.ss.data.csv</objectName>
        <size unit="byte">38559</size>
        <authentication method="MD5">a6903a7ab37ec1cb65a0f5a8d42d05f3</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url function="download">https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-nwt/124/3/841b04993c172fae59df55dda0af81ae</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>samp_date</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>samp_date</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>sample date (yyyy-mm-dd)</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>dateTime</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
              <dateTimeDomain>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum exclusive="false">1992-06-08</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">1993-08-18</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </dateTimeDomain>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NaN</code>
            <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>plot_num</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>plot_num</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>plot/base number code</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>any text</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NaN</code>
            <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>soil_temp_1cm</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>soil_temp_1cm</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>soil temperature at 1-cm depth</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NaN</code>
            <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>soil_temp_5cm</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>soil_temp_5cm</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>soil temperature at 5-cm depth</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NaN</code>
            <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>soil_temp_10cm</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>soil_temp_10cm</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>soil temperature at 10-cm depth</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NaN</code>
            <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>soil_temp_15cm</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>soil_temp_15cm</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>soil temperature at 15-cm depth</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>float</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <interval>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>celsius</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </interval>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>NaN</code>
            <codeExplanation>no data</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>1144</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
  <additionalMetadata>
    <metadata>
      <unitList>
        <unit abbreviation="C" constantToSI="273.18" id="celsius"
          multiplierToSI="1" name="celsius" parentSI="kelvin">
          <description>SI-derived unit of temperature</description>
        </unit>
      </unitList>
    </metadata>
  </additionalMetadata>
</eml:eml>
